Center for the Study of Science and Society; Records ua440.013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Center for the Study of Science and Society Records
1967-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany. Center for the Study of Science and Society
ua440.013
2.33 cubic ft.
Directed by Eugene I. Rabinowitch, the Center studied "human ecology" and interdiciplinary communications by sponsoring conferences, seminars, and symposia.
Access
Access to this collection is restricted because it is unprocessed. Portions of the collection may contain recent administrative records and/or personally identifiable information. Please contact an archivist for more information.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Administrative History
In the spring of 1966 Evan R. Collins, president of SUNYA, and Eugene Rabinowitch began a dialogue in which it was proposed that Rabinowitch come to SUNYA and help establish a research center which would be concerned with the impact of science and technology on public policy. In April 1967 the Educational Policies Council of the University Senate approved the creation of such a center, and an ad hoc planning committee was appointed. Throughout 1967 Rabinowitch working in conjunction with Eugene McLaren, assistant Dean of the Division of Science and Mathematics, organized the center and mapped out the future program and goals of the center.
By 1968 the Center for Science and the Future of Human Affairs was a reality. The Center was "organized for the purpose of orderly study of the interactions of modern science, its products and services, with the activities and aims of humankind." The Center was to develop "interdisciplinary research programs dealing with the impact of science and technology on man's personal and social existence" and considers "new approaches to education for life in the scientific age."
During 1967 and early 1968, Eugene Rabinowitch had presented a series of lectures at SUNYA. In September 1968 he was appointed as a professor of biology and chemistry at SUNYA with the additional duty of being senior advisor to the new Center.
On July 1, 1968 Victor Rabinowitch, son of Eugene Rabinowitch, was hired as director of the Center. Serving at the pleasure of SUNYA's president, Victor Rabinowitch was to be "senior administrator and manager of the operations of the Center." The director was assisted by an Advisory Committee drawn from the faculty of SUNYA.
The Center received a small planning grant from the Fleischmann Foundation in 1968. In 1969 another grant was received from the National Science Foundation; however, the Center never received sufficient support or funding from the state legislature, SUNY's central administration, or the SUNYA community.
In August 1969 the Center changed its name to the Center for the Study of Science and Society.
During its existence the Center did conduct at least four conferences. They include: The Scientific Revolution--Its Impact on Man and Society, March 1968; Evolutionary Processes, April 1970; The Integration of Science into General Education, May 1970; and, The Steady State Society, July 1971.
Frustrated by lack of support for the Center, Victor Rabinowitch, resigned as director on February 27, 1970. From March 1 to September 1, 1970 Eugene Rabinowitch was interim director of the Center. Heinz G. Pfeiffer was appointed director of the Center in April 1971, but by June 1971 he was no longer on the University payroll. The exact date that the Center ceased operations is unclear; however, this certainly happened by the time Eugene Rabinowitch left SUNYA in August 1972. The Center was finally a victim of the budget cuts and retrenchment which SUNYA underwent in the early 1970s.
Scope and Contents
The Center for the Study of Science and Society, 1966-1972, files contain the papers of Eugene Rabinowitch, Victor Rabinowitch, and Eugene H. McLaren. The files consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence, memoranda, reports, budgets, and financial statements, grant proposals, conference programs and papers, participant lists, resumes, press releases, reprints, pamphlets, leaflets, and clippings.
The files detail the history, structure, and activities of the Center. There are files relating to grants, which funded the Center. There are also files detailing the Center's relationship with other offices and departments on the SUNYA campus, as well as with SUNY Central Administration and the New York legislature. Several files detail the conferences and symposia sponsored by the Center. In addition, there are files containing materials from or about similar public policy programs at other institutions.
Arrangement of the Collection
The files are arranged alphabetically by name of individual, name of organization, or subject. A general file for each letter of the alphabet precedes files for the same letter of the alphabet (ie.: "A" precedes "Advisory Committee"). Material within the files is arranged chronologically by year, month, and day. Partially dated material is placed at the end of the month or year; undated items are placed after dated materials. Enclosures are placed after their letter of transmittal.
Political Science; Conservation and the Environment; Science and society; Science and civilization; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; State University of New York at Albany; Rabinowitch, Eugene, 1901-1973; Collins, Evan R.; State University of New York at Albany. Center for Science and the Future of Human Affairs
- A, 1967 December-1971 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 1)
- Ad Hoc Planning Committee, 1967 June-1967 November; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 2)
- Advisory Committee, Correspondence, 1968 January-1970 December; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 3)
- Advisory Committee, Members' Vitae, Undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 4)
- Annual Report, 1969/1970; 1970 January-1970 February; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 5)
- Anthropology Department, 1970 January-1970 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 6)
- B, 1967 April-1971 April; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 7)
- Blum, Harold, 1968 March-1970 January; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 8)
- Brim Report, 1969 August-1969 October (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 9)
- Budget and Finance, 1967 April-1971 May; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 10)
- Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1969 April-1971 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 11)
- Business, School of, 1970 July (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 12)
- C, 1968 February-1971 May; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 13)
- Case Western Reserve University, Science, Technology and Public Policy Program, Undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 14)
- Center for Government Policy Analysis, 1970 October; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 15)
- Center for International Programs and Services, 1967 October-1968 November (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 16)
- Center for International Programs and Services, 1969 January-1971 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 17)
- Comparative Development Studies Center, 1969 March-1970 July; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 18)
- Cornell University, Science, Technology and Society Progra, Aug 1969 - July 1970, 1969 August-1970 July (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 19)
- Criminal Justice, School of, 1968 January-1968 April (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 20)
- D, 1966 October-1971 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 21)
- Development of Science and Technology Seminar, 1969 February-1969 November (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 22)
- Director, Search for, 1970 February-1970 November (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 23)
- E, 1969 April-1971 May (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 24)
- Eastern Regional Conference on Science and Technology for Public Programs, 1969 February-1970 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 25)
- Economics Department, 1968 May-1971 August; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 26)
- English Department, 1970 July (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 27)
- Environmental Issues, 1968 November-1969 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 28)
- Evolutionary Processes Conference, 1969 October-1970 September (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 29)
- F, 1968 October-1971 January; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 30)
- Five Rivers Program, 1970 September-1970 October (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 31)
- Fleischmann Foundation, Correspondence, 1967 September-1971 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 32)
- Fleischmann Foundation, Grant, Financial Statements, 1968 June-1972 May (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 33)
- Fleischmann Foundation, Grant, Project Director's Report, 1968 February-1969 August (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 34)
- Fleischmann Foundation, Grant, Proposals, 1967 February-1967 September (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 35)
- Fleischmann Foundation, Grant, Proposals, 1967 (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 36)
- Fleischmann Foundation, Grant, Proposals, 1970 June (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 37)
- G, 1968 April-1971 January (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 38)
- Graduate School of Public Affairs, 1968 October-1971 June (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 39)
- H, 1968 October-1970 September; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 40)
- Hall, Warren A., 1969 September-1971 December (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 41)
- Hirshom, Seth, "Center for the Study of Science and Society: A Case Study,", 1972 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 42)
- Horn, Axel, 1969 March-1970 October (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 43)
- Hudson Institute, 1969 February-1970 January (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 44)
- Institute for International Development, State University of New York, 1969 January-1969 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 45)
- Institute on Man and Science, 1968 September-1971 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 46)
- Integration of Science Into General Education Symposium, 1969 July-1970 June; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 47)
- International Center for Integrative Studies, 1968 February-1970 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 48)
- International Center for Insect Physiology and Ecology, 1968 November-1970 February (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 49)
- J, 1968 April-1970 November (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 50)
- K, 1968 June-1970 February; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 51)
- L, 1968 July-1970 (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 52)
- Levey, Martin, 1968 November-1969 March; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 53)
- Library Acquisitions, 1968 July-1971 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 54)
- M, 1967 September-1972 February; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 55)
- McHale, John, 1967 August-1967 November (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 56)
- McHale, John, 1969 January-1969 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 57)
- McHale, John, 1969 March (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 58)
- McLaren, Eugene H, 1967 January-1970 February; undated (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 59)
- Man and Beast: Comparative Social Behavior Symposium, Smithsonian Institution, 1969 May (Box 1 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 60)
- Manifesto, Mission and Management: A Position Paper, 1970 October (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 1)
- Manifesto, Mission and Management: A Position Paper, Undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 2)
- Manpower Report on Sponsored Research, 1968 April-1968 July (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous, 1966 October-1969 October; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 4)
- N, 1968 April-1970 October; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 5)
- National Academy of Sciences, 1969 March-1970 February (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 6)
- National Environmental Library, 1971 April (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 7)
- National Science Foundation, Correspondence, 1969 July-1970 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 8)
- National Science Foundation, Correspondence, 1970 June-1972 January (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 9)
- National Science Foundation, Grant, Financial Statements, 1969 September-1972 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 10)
- National Science Foundation, Grant, Project Director's Report, 1969 June-1969 August (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 11)
- National Science Foundation, Grant Proposal, 1969; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 12)
- National Water Commission, 1969 May-1969 September (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 13)
- New York State Legislature, 1970 January-1971 February; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 14)
- New York State Science and Technology Foundation, 1969 December-1970 November (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 15)
- New York University, Management of Science and Technology Course, 1967-1969 February (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 16)
- Nonviolent Conflict Resolution Forum, 1970 May-1970 December; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 17)
- Northern Arizona Field Research Expedition, 1969 April-1969 July (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 18)
- O, 1969 January-1970 February (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 19)
- Ozarow, Vernon, 1968 April-1969 November; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 20)
- P, 1967 November-1971 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 21)
- Personnel, 1968 May-1971 January (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 22)
- Pfeiffer, Heinz G., 1970 September-1971 April (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 23)
- Philosophy Department, 1968 June; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 24)
- Physical Facilities, Feb 1968 - Dec 1970, nd (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 25)
- Prescott College, Contemporary Affairs,Center, April - May 1969, 1969 April-1969 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 26)
- President's Office, 1966 March-1971 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 27)
- Program on Aging, 1968 December-1969 April (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 28)
- Proposal for Center, 1966; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 29)
- Prospectus, 1970 June-1971 March; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 30)
- Publicity, 1968 March-1970 February (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 31)
- Purdue University, Science and Public Policy Program, 1967 July-1969 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 32)
- R, 1967 December-1971 May; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 33)
- Rabinowitch, Eugene, 1966 November-1971 December; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 34)
- Rabinowitch, Victor, 1968 February-1969 January (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 35)
- Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 1968 December-1971 March; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 36)
- Research Office, 1967 April-1971 May; Undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 37)
- Russian and Soviet Scientific Thought, 1968 (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 38)
- S, 1968 March-1972 February (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 39)
- St. Andrews Presbyterian College, 1970 May (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 40)
- Science and Development Conference, 1969 August-1970 October (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 41)
- Science and Mathematics Division, 1968 November-1969 July (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 42)
- Science and Public Policies Study Group, Correspondence, 1967 May-1971 January (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 43)
- Science and Public Policies Study Group, Newsletter, 1969 November-1971 March (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 44)
- The Scientific Revolution and Man's Situation, Course, 1968 June-1969 June; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 45)
- The Scientific Revolution: Its Impact on Man and Society - Correspondence, Sept 1966 - 1967, 1966 September-1967 (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 46)
- The Scientific Revolution: Its Impact on Man and Society - Correspondence, 1968 January-1968 February (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 47)
- The Scientific Revolution: Its Impact on Man and Society - Correspondence, 1968 March-1969 January; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 48)
- The Scientific Revolution: Its Impact on Man and Society - Financial Matters, 1968 March-1968 June; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 49)
- The Scientific Revolution: Its Impact on Man and Society - Miscellaneous, 1967-1968; undated (Box 2 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 50)
- Report of Conference, 1968 March-1968 April (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 1)
- Seminar on Change, Proposal by James W. Corbett, 1969 September; undated (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 2)
- Sloan Foundation, 1969 October-1969 December (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 3)
- Social Invention Conference, SUNY Binghamton, 1969 February-1969 May (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 4)
- Stanford University, Political and Social Issues Workshop, 1969 (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 5)
- State University of New York, Central Administration, 1967 January-1971 May; undated (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 6)
- The Steady State Society Summer Institute - Correspondence, 1970 October-1971 August (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 7)
- The Steady State Society Summer Institute - Miscellaneous, 1966 February-1971 July; undated (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 8)
- The Steady State Society Summer Institute - Proposal, 1971 February-1971 March; undated (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 9)
- The Steady State Society Summer Institute - Readings, 1971 July (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 10)
- T, 1969 May-1970 September (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 11)
- Territory of Man, 1968 October-1968 December (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 12)
- Trends in Science Policy Seminar, Battelle Seattle Research Center, 1969 March-1969 April (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 13)
- U, 1968 January-1972 June (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 14)
- Unified Science Course, 1967 February (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 15)
- University of California, Davis, Political Science Department, 1968 January (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 16)
- University of Michigan, 1967 June-1969 September (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 17)
- University of Virginia, Center for the Study of Science, Technology and Public Policy, 1968 August-1970 June (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 18)
- V, 1968 December-1969 November (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 19)
- W, 1968 October-1971 October (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 20)
- Washington University, International Development and Technology Center, 1968 July (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 21)
- Working Group on Science and Public Policy, Undated (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 22)
- Z, 1968 October-1971 April (Box 3 (Center for the Study of Science and Society Record), Folder 23)